<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<article>
    
	<informaltable><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry><anchor id="tex2html477"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="next.png" width="37">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>next</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html473"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="up.png" width="26">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>up</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html467"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="prev.png" width="63">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>previous</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html475"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="contents.png" width="65">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>contents</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></entry><entry><ulink url="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=referer"><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="http://www.w3.org/Icons/valid-xhtml10">31</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>Valid XHTML 1.0!</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></ulink> <ulink url="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/"><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/images/vcss">31</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>Valid CSS!</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></ulink></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis role="b">Next:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html478"/>User Input <emphasis role="b">Up:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html474"/>izpack-doc <emphasis role="b">Previous:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html468"/>Advanced Features <emphasis role="b"><anchor id="tex2html476"/>Contents</emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody></tgroup></informaltable>
	
    
     
    <para><?db2html element="br"?><anchor id="CHILD_linkS"/><emphasis role="strong">Subsections</emphasis> </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>
     	<anchor id="tex2html4790"/>Creating Your Own Panels 
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html479"/>How to get started
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html480"/>Next Steps
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html481"/>Access to the Variable Substitution System
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html482"/>Controlling Flow
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html483"/>Reading XML
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html484"/>Supporting Classes
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html485"/>Panels that are not visible
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html486"/>A word about building IzPack
          </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
        <?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <anchor id="tex2html487"/>The <literal>IzPanel</literal> Class 
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html488"/>UML Diagram
          </para></listitem><listitem><para>
            <anchor id="tex2html489"/>Description
          </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
        <?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <anchor id="tex2html490"/>The <literal>Internationalization</literal> of custom panels
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    
    <hr xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
    <title>
      Creating Your Own Panels
    </title>
    <para>
      In IzPack all of the actual work of installing an application is done in panels. The IzPack framework is primarily there to support the operation of the panels and to manage the navigation
      through the installation process. This enables a user to decide which operations are carried out during an installation and the order in which they are carried out, simply by listing the
      appropriate panels in the desired order.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      As far as extending the functionality of IzPack is concerned, the result of this design is that new functionality can be integrated by adding new panels to the framework and then listing them
      in the install spec. Because the existing panels all have a visible GUI and because the term panel hints at something visible, it is not obvious that a panel does not have to contain any
      visible GUI to function in this framework. There are more details on this subject later on in this chapter.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/><section id="SECTION00701000000000000000"><title>
      How to get started
    </title>
    <para>
      To get started with writing your own panels, it is best to place all the IzPack code into a separate working directory, from where you can compile it. Then try to compile the code as is and get
      that to work.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      The next step would be to have a look at another panel implementation, so you can see how things are done. Make sure you look at the less complicated panels, as the panels with advanced
      features will only be confusing. All the code for building UI and such, only detracts from the essentials of what a panel needs to do. This means that you shouldn't start with <literal>
      UserInputPanel</literal> or <literal>ShortcutPanel</literal>. <literal>HelloPanel</literal> is probably a much better choice at this stage. The source code for panels is located at:<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      <literal>/src/lib/com/izforge/izpack/panels</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      You will find that all panels are derived from <literal>IzPanel</literal>; do the same thing with your new panel. Please note that the <literal>IzPanel</literal> class itself is located in the <literal>
      com.izforge.izpack.installer</literal> package but your panels need to belong to <literal>com.izforge.izpack.panels</literal>. Perhaps you can just copy the code of a panel, remove all the functional stuff
      and then start filling in your own code. Start with something very simple to begin with, just to see how it works. The implementation is really quite straight forward.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00702000000000000000"><title>
      Next Steps
    </title>
    <para>
      Once you have a successful compilation, you must place the compiled result of your panel code at a special place, so that the installer compiler can fetch it when building an installer that
      uses your panel. Go to:<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      <literal>/bin/panels</literal><?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      You will see that there is a subdirectory for each panel. Make a subdirectory for your new panel with the exact same name as your panel and place your compiled panel code there.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      Once this is accomplished, you are ready to use your panel in an installer. Just list it in the spec file like any other panel, compile and in theory it will show up when running the installer.
      Once you made it this far, you can dig deeper and get going with your specific needs.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      Oh, and one other thing: If you think the your code might be useful for a larger audience, please think about a contribution to IzPack.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00703000000000000000"><title>
      Access to the Variable Substitution System
    </title>
    <para>
      One thing many developers ask about is how to get access to the variable substitution system. This is not surprising, because customizing an installation for a particular target environment is
      one of the most important functions of an installer and the variable substitution system plays a big part in this operation.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      You can get access to the variable substitution system through the protected variable <literal>idata</literal> in <literal>IzPanel</literal>. This variable is of the type <literal>InstallData</literal>, which is in turn
      subclassed from <literal>AutomatedInstallData</literal>. The Javadoc documentation will give you more details on these classes. Of particular interest in this context are the methods <literal>
      getVariable()</literal>, <literal>setVariable()</literal> and <literal>getVariableValueMap()</literal> in <literal>AutomatedInstallData</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00704000000000000000"><title>
      Controlling Flow
    </title>
    <para>
      Some of the interesting methods in <literal>com.izforge.izpack.InstallerFrame</literal> that you might want to explore are <literal>lockPrevButton()</literal> and <literal>lockNextButton()</literal>. They allow you to block
      the use of the button to move back to the previous panel and the button that moves to the next panel respectively. Being able to control the availability of these buttons to the user is
      important if one of your panels performs a task where the effects cannot be undone. If the user would navigate back to the previous panel your installation might get into an unknown or even
      unstable state. On the other hand, if the operations in one panel vitally depend that a task in the previous panel is completed, then you should block the use of the next button until that task
      is completed.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00705000000000000000"><title>
      Reading XML
    </title>
    <para>
      If you need configuration files for your panel you would want to use XML for that purpose. To read XML files you should use NanoXML, as it is guaranteed to be available at installation time. In
      fact, all of the IzPack infrastructure uses NanoXML to read XML files. First you should read the NanoXML documentation. The documentation is included as PDF file with the IzPack distribution,
      have a look in <literal>/doc/nanoxml</literal>. In addition to that, the Javadoc-generated class documentation is an excellent resource to get help on NanoXML. And then, there is always the code of other
      panels to see practical examples. Generally, it is a much simpler matter to use NanoXML then to use the DOM included with the Java distribution, so don't hesitate to explore NanoXML.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00706000000000000000"><title>
      Supporting Classes
    </title>
    <para>
      If your panel requires any supporting classes that are part of the panels package, then you must place the *.class files into the same directory with your panel .class file.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to have supporting classes that are not part of the panels package. In fact, these classes don't even have to be in the <literal>com.izpack...</literal> tree. You simply have to
      ensure that the *.class files are located in the proper directory structure inside <literal>/lib/installer.jar</literal>. If this is done, they will be available at install time. For your first
      experiments you can simply compile your classes and add them to the *.jar file using the jar tool or a zip utility. However, ultimately it is much easier to use Ant and the IzPack build script
      to accomplish this task.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00707000000000000000"><title>
      Panels that are not visible
    </title>
    <para>
      If you have a task that needs to be performed at a particular step in the installation process, but that does not need any user interaction, you can implement a panel that is not visible. To
      implement this, you should first familiarize yourself with the Javadoc documentation of <literal>com.izforge.izpack.InstallerFrame</literal>. In your panel code you get access to the right instance of
      <literal>InstallerFrame</literal> through the protected variable <literal>parent</literal> in <literal>IzFrame</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      To begin with, do not configure any UI. In other words, do not set a layout and do not place any GUI elements on your panel. In this context the method <literal>skipPanel()</literal> is what gets the job
      done. In your <literal>panelActivate()</literal> method you simply perform your task and then call <literal>parent.skipPanel()</literal>. This gets the job done without the user being aware that there was another
      panel in the flow.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00708000000000000000"><title>
      A word about building IzPack
    </title>
    <para>
      If you don't already use Jakarta Ant to support your development work, i highly recommend you have a look at it. It is a great help in organizing practically all routine tasks connected with
      building and packaging your application. For example, building and getting IzPack ready for distribution is not a straight forward process but with Ant this all comes down to starting a single
      command. In addition, IzPack provides its own Ant task, which supports the integration of building a complete installer into your regular build scripts. You can find more details about this in
      the chapter about advanced features. To get a look at Ant you can visit the following link: <literal><anchor id="tex2html28"/>
      http://ant.apache.org/index.html</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      You can find the Ant build script for IzPack itself at:<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      <literal>/src/build.xml</literal><?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <title>
      The <literal>IzPanel</literal> Class
    </title>
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00711000000000000000"><title>
      UML Diagram
    </title>
    
      <informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="img6.png" width="573">555</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>\fbox{\includegraphics[scale=0.5]{img/ch5-izpanel}}</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure>
    
    <para/></section><section id="SECTION00712000000000000000"><title>
      Description
    </title>
    <para>
      The two data members are : the install data (refer to the <literal>InstallData</literal> Javadoc reference) and a reference to the parent installer frame.<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <para>
      The methods have the following functionality :<?db2html element="br"?>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="i">(constructor)</emphasis> : called just after the language selection dialog. All the panels are constructed at this time and then the installer is shown. So be aware of the fact that the installer
        window is <emphasis role="b">not</emphasis> yet visible when the panel is created. If you need to do some work when the window is created, it is in most cases better do it in <literal>panelActivate</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>isValidated</literal> returns <literal>true</literal> if the user is allowed to go a step further in the installation process. Returning <literal>false</literal> will lock it. For instance the LicencePanel
        returns <literal>true</literal> only if the user has agreed with the license agreement. The default is to return <literal>true</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>panelActivate</literal> is called when the panel becomes active. This is the best place for most initialization tasks. The default is to do nothing.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>makeXMLData</literal> is called to build the automated installer data. The default is to do nothing. <literal>panelRoot</literal> refers to the node in the XML tree where you can save your data. Each
        panel is given a node. You can organize it as you want with the markups you want starting from <literal>panelRoot</literal>. It's that simple.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>runAutomated</literal> is called by an automated-mode installation. Each panel is called and can do its job by picking the data collected during a previous installation as saved in <literal>
        panelRoot</literal> by <literal>makeXMLData</literal>.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>setInitialFocus</literal> with this method it is possible to set a hint which component should be get the focus at activation of the panel. It is only a hint. Not all components are supported.
        For more information see java.awt.Component.requestFocusInWindow or java.awt.Component.requestFocus if the VM version is less than 1.4.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>getInitialFocus</literal> returns the component which should be get the focos at activation of the panel. If no component was set, null returns.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>getSummaryBody</literal> this method will be called from the SummaryPanel to get the summary of this class which should be placed in the SummaryPanel. The returned text should not contain a
        caption of this item. The caption will be requested from the method getCaption. If null returns, no summary for this panel will be enerated. Default behaviour is to return null.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>
        <literal>getSummaryCaption</literal> this method will be called from the SummaryPanel to get the caption for this class which should be placed in the SummaryPanel. Default behaviour is to return the
        string given by langpack for the key ClassName.summaryCaption.<?db2html element="br"?>
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Additionally, there are some helper methods to simplify grid bag layout handling and creation of some common used components.
    </para>
    <title>
      The <literal>Internationalization</literal> of custom panels
    </title>
   <para> A common way to define language dependant messages for custom panels is to add entries into the common langpacks which are stored in the directory </para>
<programlisting>
[IzPackRoot]/bin/langpacks/installer
</programlisting>
   <para> New with version 3.8 is the possibility to define a resource for custom langpacks. Define e.g. </para>
<programlisting>
&lt;resources&gt;
    ...
    &lt;res id="CustomLangpack.xml_deu" 
        src="myConfigSubPath/CustomLangpack_deu.xml"/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/resources&gt;
</programlisting>
   <para> in the install.xml file.The id should be written as shown, the file sub path and name can be other than in the example. This file should be use the same DTD as the common langpack. For each
    language a separate file with the ISO3 extension in the id should be used. </para>
    <hr xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
       
	<informaltable><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry><anchor id="tex2html477"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="next.png" width="37">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>next</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html473"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="up.png" width="26">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>up</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html467"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="prev.png" width="63">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>previous</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure> <anchor id="tex2html475"/><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="contents.png" width="65">24</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>contents</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></entry><entry><ulink url="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=referer"><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="http://www.w3.org/Icons/valid-xhtml10">31</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>Valid XHTML 1.0!</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></ulink> <ulink url="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/"><informalfigure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/images/vcss">31</imagedata></imageobject><caption><para>Valid CSS!</para></caption></mediaobject></informalfigure></ulink></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis role="b">Next:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html478"/>User Input <emphasis role="b">Up:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html474"/>izpack-doc <emphasis role="b">Previous:</emphasis> <anchor id="tex2html468"/>Advanced Features <emphasis role="b"><anchor id="tex2html476"/>Contents</emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody></tgroup></informaltable>
	<address xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	
      Julien Ponge 2005-05-24
    </address>
  <para/></section></article>
